<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
"http://maven.apache.org/dtd/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Installation Notes</title>

    <author email="me@simonwallner.at">Simon Wallner</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
  	<section name="Release Note">
		<p>The current release of Jake uses mocks to simulate inter client communication and parts of the synchronization. That means that it is not network enabled but demonstrates its features and capabilities</p>
		<subsection name="Constraints/Known issues">
			<ul>
				<li>File and folder names must comply to the following expression: [a-zA-Z0-9\-_.]+</li>
				<li>User Names must contain the '@' character to be a valid userid</li>
				<li>Do not change the userid of the local user.</li>
				<li>You might experience the interface to be not as fast as possible.</li>
			</ul>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="Hints">
			<ul>
				<li>To successfully log in use a userId for both userid and password.</li>
				<li>Remote users containing a 's' before the '@' in their userid are always online</li>
				<li>Remote users containing a 'n' before the '@' in their userid push a new version of 'Projektauftrag/Lastenheft.txt' upen every logsync.</li>
			</ul>
		</subsection>
		<subsection name="a sample Case">
			<p>To fully appreciate the features of jake, we'd like to provide a short sample case that covers all aspects of team synchronization and conflict resolution. Due to the use of mocks some steps are non-trivial and therefore a little help in form of this step-by-step guide may be helpful.</p>
			<ul>
				<li>Start jake and create a new project by selecting a project folder and entering a user name, e.g. "me@host".</li>
				<li>create to following project members: chris@host, dominik@host, johannes@host, peter@host, philipp@host, simon@host</li>
				<li>Log in to the network by either clicking "Network -> sign in..." in the menu bar or by clicking the small connection icon in the lower right corner of jake. To successfully log in uns the same user name for both id and password.</li>
				<li>After pressing the refresh button a new file "Projektauftrag/Lastenheft.txt" will be displayed in the file browser.</li>
				<li>Select the new file, right click and select "Pull file" from the kontext menu to pull the file and transfer it from the remote project member.</li>
				<li>Open the file by either double-clicking on it or by choosing "open" from the context menu.</li>
				<li>Change the file in an external application and safe the changes</li>
				<li>Issue a "push" on the file, i.e choose "announce file" from the context menu.</li>
				<li>Change the file once more.</li>
				<li>Try syncing the file by pressing the refresh button.</li>
				<li>A version conflict occurred! The resolve Dialog is shown. You may inspect both files a choose which one to keep.</li>
			</ul>
			<p>That has been a short walkthrough through a typical "team sync" case. All other features of jake should be pretty straight forward self explanatory. Just click your way through it!</p>
		</subsection>
  	</section>
</body>
</document>
