<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//Apache Software Foundation//DTD XDOC 1.0//EN"
"http://www.apache.org/dtds/xdoc_1_0.dtd">
<document>
  <properties>
    <title>Requirements</title>
    <author email="me@simonwallner.at">Simon Wallner</author>
  </properties>

  <body>
    <section name="Requirements">
    	This page contains all functional and nonfunctional requirements.
    	<subsection name="Functional Requirements">
    		<ul>
    			<li>manage project members</li>
    			<li>metadata like phone number, department, role, competence may be added to a person.</li>
    			<li>send messages to other project members</li>
    			<li>read messages</li>
    			<li>data version conflicts must be resolved between project members. If conflict occur, the application notifies the user and provides tools and help to manually resolve the conflict.</li>
    			<li>The networking and synchronisation functionality are interfaces with mock-ob implementations. Only user interaction for conflict resolving will be implemented.</li>
    			<li>Data may be tagged with metadata and organised in categories by various keywords.</li>
    			<li>Data used in the application remains usable from outside the application.</li>
    			<li>A list of files (not necessarily the files themselves) is available even if the application is offline.</li>
    			<li>changes in local data are propagated (half)automatically to all other project members.</li>
    			<li>Every change made to a file has a comment, a time-stamp and a hash.</li>
    			<li>The user may choose between automatic or manual push/pull.</li>
    		</ul>
    	</subsection>
    	<subsection name="Nonfunctional Requirements">
    		<ul>
    			<li>It is not required to configure and run a central server to fully use the application. Setting up the application is easy even for users with minor computer experience.</li>
    			<li>The application will run on the Windows, Linux and Mac plattform.</li>
    			<li>The application must not corrupt data under any circumstances.</li>
    			<li>Using the application can be learned quickly and easily.</li>
    			<li>The application is largely self-explenatory.</li>
    		</ul>
    	</subsection>
    </section>
    <section name="Changelog">
		<table>
			<tr>
			  <td>No.</td>
			  <td>Date</td>
			  <td>Author</td>
			  <td>Change</td>
			</tr>
	
			<tr>
			  <td>1</td>
			  <td>2008-04-17</td>
			  <td>SW</td>
			  <td>created</td>
			</tr>
		  </table>
      </section>
  </body>
</document>
